Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes, 1
  - Magnus, Charles--States: North Carolina. (Offsite-box 3, Item 7)
    Angel next to American flag and Devil holding North Carolina state seal. White envelope with gold ink. Images on left and center.
  - Magnus, Charles--States: Louisiana. (Offsite-box 3, Item 5)
    Angel next to American flag and Devil holding Louisiana state seal. White envelope with gold ink. Images on left and center.
  - Magnus, Charles--States: (Offsite-box 3, Item 35)
    For the Union.
  - Magnus, Charles--Washington, D.C.: Long Bridge, Washington, by Moonlight No. 3 (Offsite-box 3, Item 6)
    A view of Long Bridge, with guard houses and a few soldiers present. It is otherwise deserted. Cream envelope with copper ink. Image on entire front of envelope.
  - Magnus, Charles--Washington, D.C.: Long Bridge, Washington, by Moonlight No. 1 (Offsite-box 3, Item 4)
    Horses pulling a cart with a cannon on it over the bridge, while soldiers with bayonets look on or rest against the side. Cream envelope with copper ink. Image on entire front of envelope.
  - Magnus, Charles--Washington, D.C.: Long Bridge, Washington, by Moonlight No. 2 (Offsite-box 3, Item 5)
    Horses pulling a cart with a cannon on it over the bridge, while soldiers with bayonets look on or huddle against the side. A small building is visible. Cream envelope with copper ink. Image on entire front of envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: We stand by our flag. (Offsite-box 7, Item 22)
    Confederate flag. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Unite or die. (Offsite-box 7, Item 36)
    Snake labeled with the names of the Confederate states. White envelope with black ink. Image on top.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Away down south in Dixie. (Offsite-box 7, Item 25)
    Horse-drawn cart carrying bales of cotton, with two men riding and another walking beside it. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left-top.
    Creator: Falen, G. W., printer
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Bold but wary. (Offsite-box 7, Item 26)
    Shield with star, moon and palm tree. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: C.S.A (Offsite-box 7, Item 1)
    Confederate flag. White envelope with colored and gold ink. Image in center.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Confederate States of America, Post Office Department, Auditor's Office. (Offsite-box 7, Item 2)
    Stationary from Auditors office. No image. White envelope with black ink. Text across top. Addressed to E. E. Alexander, Esq., P.M.(?) Pickens, C.H., S. C.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: C. S. A. Our throne. (Offsite-box 7, Item 45)
    Confederate officer sitting on a bale of cotton. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Southern rights will be defended by Southern men. (Offsite-box 7, Item 12)
    Creator: Mullen, J., publisher
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Don'e tread on us. (Offsite-box 7, Item 6)
    Two Confederate flags, crossing and joined with a snake, over the state seal of South Carolina. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Southern rights. (Offsite-box 7, Item 5)
    Confederate shield. White envelope with colored ink. Image in center (vertical orientation.)
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: The cotton plant - king of the South. (Offsite-box 7, Item 46)
    Cotton plant with decorative frame. White envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: The sunny South our country. The sunny South our country. (Offsite-box 7, Item 23)
    Baby sitting on a globe holding the Confederate flag and strangling a snake labeled "abolition." Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: We are in the field, and the bars are up! (Offsite-box 7, Item 16)
    Confederate flag. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: [Confederate Liberty.] [Confederate Liberty.] (Offsite-box 7, Item 43)
    Liberty holding a Confederate flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Allen & Boyer
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Gather around your country's flag. Gather around your country's flag. (Offsite-box 7, Item 44)
    Confederate soldier on horseback with sword drawn. White envelope with black ink. Image on left. Addressed to Mr. Jesse Mematian (?), Arnold Mill, Pickens District, South Carolina. Confederate stamp.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: "If any one attempts to haul down the American flag, shoot him on the spot." (Offsite-box 7, Item 35)
    Farcical design of Abraham Lincoln being shot by a cannon at close range. He concaves under the force. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: Its thunder tones shall arouse the freeman. (Offsite-box 7, Item 37)
    Cannon in front of the Confederate flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate: [Confederate flag.] (Offsite-box 7, Item 27)
    Confederate flag. Addressed to Mrs. Nancy Thigpen (?) (?wood),. Postmark from Georgia. White envelope with colored ink. Image on top-left.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: What the South shall see! (Offsite-box 7, Item 23)
    Davis is hung at the 'Traitors Platform'. Angel sits atop three coffins holding a Union shield. Liberty has a banner with Lincoln, Scott & Anderson on it. Disunion snake slithers around her. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The Man who conceived C.S.A. (Offsite-box 7, Item 58)
    Image of foppish, overdressed man. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Hayes, J. E.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: A general of the C. S. A. army preparing to meet Gen. McClellan. (Offsite-box 7, Item 94)
    A large image of an officer in uniform, putting on his gloves in preparation and a tiny image of the same officer running away. Yellow envelope with black ink. Large figure on left with small figure on bottom-right.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Fac-Simile of the New Confederate Bond (Offsite-box 7, Item 42)
    Drawing of an I.O.U. with Jefferson Davis thumbing his nose on it, surrounded by the text wrapping around the outside border. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Now, boasting Southron, hold thine own,… (Offsite-box 7, Item 62)
    A Southern being held around the neck by a uniformed Northern soldier. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side and top of envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The Southerner as He Was. (Offsite-box 7, Item 50)
    A stereotypical version of the Southern gentleman, with large hat, smoking with a drink on the table, sitting outside. Cream envelope with red and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: A member of the C.S.A. Alligator Ranglers, who is to make 5 of the "Northern mudsils" run. We don't see it. (Offsite-box 7, Item 86)
    A silhouette of a stereotypical Southerner with a whip, a saber, bottle with Old B. _?? on it and JD on his hat. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Gates, James
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Secession (Offsite-box 7, Item 68)
    A hot air balloon entitled Secession bursts and drops people out of the basket below it. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The result of playing with dangerous weapons-the sure result Traitors beware! (Offsite-box 7, Item 72)
    A gun blows up and knocks a man onto his back while the exploding pieces of the gun fly around him. One piece is entitled Secession.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: New Southern Coin (Offsite-box 7, Item 35)
    Coin design with three links of chain with I O U in each of the links and 1861 underneath it. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The flying artillery of the C. S. A. (Offsite-box 7, Item 91)
    Union army advancing as the Confederate army flees. Orange envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: One of the C.S.A. generals whose quiet will soon be disturbed. (Offsite-box 7, Item 53)
    A man sits reading a paper in an easy chair with his slippers on. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: A Convention of Secessionists after the War (Offsite-box 7, Item 46)
    Five unwell and frazzled looking men sit around a table with smelling salts and gin. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on entire front of envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: One of the F.F.V.'s Colonel of Dysentery… (Offsite-box 7, Item 61)
    Bearded colonel stands at attention with his saber and a bottle in his pocket. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Secession Cavalry (Offsite-box 7, Item 87)
    Under the flag of skull & crossbones, the cavalry rides in on the shoulders of slaves. White envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Owe Never Pay Never (Offsite-box 7, Item 38)
    Coin with figures of Lincoln (?) handing a paper to a man who is pointing a gun at him and thumbing his nose. Slaves toil in the background while a man with a whip oversees. Beige envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: A "Horse Marine" of the C.S.A. (Offsite-box 7, Item 48)
    A plump figure with a naval hat on sits atop a wooden horse with a spyglass in his hand. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Secessionists leaving the Union. (Offsite-box 7, Item 63)
    A tree entitled Union with two men sitting on a branch entitled Secession whilst they are sawing it off. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The Union shall exist as long as the Compass points to the North. (Offsite-box 7, Item 88)
    A simple drawing of a compass pointing north. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: To Cure Rebellion (Offsite-box 7, Item 30)
    Giant bomb that's about to go off. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: On the Road to Washington (Offsite-box 7, Item 19)
    A long row of gallows with bodies hanging from them, with Confederate names above them. The Capitol is in the background. White envelope with red ink. Image is on top and patterned over the entire front.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: "Infernal Machine," found at Washington (Offsite-box 7, Item 26)
    On a desk, a long scroll hangs down, with the terms Compromise, Southern Rights, Crittenden, W(V)allandingham and Saulsbury on it. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Plenty of Drumming, but no Recruits (Offsite-box 7, Item 44)
    A uniformed drummer with C.S.A on his cap. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: "Jewels" found at Alexandria… (Offsite-box 7, Item 7)
    Drawings of handcuffs, shackles and chains. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The Result of Secession. (Offsite-box 7, Item 66)
    Two African American slaves converse in a public square. One is dress in a fine suit and hat, the other in work clothes. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side and top of envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Death to Traitors (Offsite-box 7, Item 14)
    Soldier figures, hanged men and American flags make up the phrase 'Death to Traitors'. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on top of envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Army Rations of the Southern Confederacy. (Offsite-box 7, Item 83)
    A man is picking a basket full of cotton out of a larger bale. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: E. Cogan
  - Miscellaneous Secession: What they must soon come to. (Offsite-box 7, Item 81)
    A member of the C.S.A. afloat on a barrel. He is ragged, emaciated and holding an empty bottle. A tattered C.S.A. flag is also on the barrel. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: The Lock and Key (Offsite-box 7, Item 6)
    A padlock with 'slavery' on it being picked by a bayonet point. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: One of the "Southern Chivalry" after… (Offsite-box 7, Item 56)
    Two faces with differing expressions. First one is plump and happy, second is utterly shocked, as hears of President Lincoln's message. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: Secession States--Present Secession States--Future (Offsite-box 7, Item 51)
    Present: a line of dapper men with linked arms looking happy Future: the same men are chained together and sad. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Secession: A rebel attack on pickin's. (Offsite-box 7, Item 77)
    An emaciated Confederate soldier gnaws on a bone. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: "Don't see it." (Offsite-box 7, Item 54)
    Two bedraggled country-gentlemen are talking to each other. Cream envelope with red and black ink. Image on left side, and address form is on the right side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: "Strike home! And the world shall revere us, As heroes descended from heroes." (Offsite-box 7, Item 56)
    Appears to be the top of a fort, with an American flag, guns, cannons, bombs and bayonets all present, with a banner with 1861 on it. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: April 19th 1775 (Offsite-box 7, Item 27)
    Depictions of the battles of Lexington during the Revolutionary War and the Battle of Baltimore in the Civil War. White envelope with brown ink. Image is across top of entire envelope.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Union (Offsite-box 7, Item 16)
    'Union' surrounded by a floral design with a banner running through it with all the states in the country written on the banner. Two cherubs are holding up the banner amidst the flowers. Cream envelope with multi-colored inks. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The Strong Arm of the North (Offsite-box 7, Item 45)
    A large muscular arm holds a hammer. Cream envelope with purple ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The Real Declaration of Independence which took place in Phila., July 4th, 1776. (Offsite-box 7, Item 26)
    A rendering of Colonial Era Declaration of Independence signing. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The Unity of the Government which constitutes you (Offsite-box 7, Item 24)
    Decorative border and pattern on the entire front of envelope. The Motto is wrapped around the outside border. White envelope with gray ink.
  - Miscellaneous Union: United Forever (Offsite-box 7, Item 79)
    A shield with Union and Secession states on interlocking rings. An eagle sits atop an American flag with a banner reading "E Pluribus" is in its mouth. White envelope with red, blue and black ink. Image on left side and across top.
    Creator: Harbach & Brother
  - Miscellaneous Union: Corn (Not Cotton) is King. (Offsite-box 7, Item 38)
    A man gathering large sheaves of corn. Cream envelope with purple ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The "Union" Pill in operation, working without the quack nostrums of Doctor Davis & Co. (Offsite-box 7, Item 31)
    A giant Union pill comes to wreck havoc with the other medicines, entitled Confederate Mixture, Davis Lotion and Secession Pills. The medicines are anthropomorphised. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The Results of Uncle Sam's Government. Peace, Plenty and Prosperity. (Offsite-box 7, Item 42)
    A man plowing a field in front of a house. A woman has crops in her arms. Horses and hay bales are present. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: "Proclaim Liberty Throughout All the Land, Unto the Inhabitants Thereof." (Offsite-box 7, Item 58)
    Liberty Bell with the word 'Liberty' across it. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: From the Hammer to the Sabre. (Offsite-box 7, Item 49)
    A strong arm wielding a saber. White envelope with multi-colored inks. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The New Quaker Bonnet, 1861. (Offsite-box 7, Item 86)
    A Quaker bonnet made out of the American flag. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: "Young America" (Offsite-box 7, Item 75)
    Child of the North is playing with a toy, child of the South is smoking and sitting on a barrel of cognac. Beige envelope with brown ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: My God first, my country next, and then my family. (Offsite-box 7, Item 51)
    Allegorical pictures of the omniscient eye in the sky, American flag and a house. White envelope with black ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Union Forever (Offsite-box 7, Item 36)
    In a rather pastoral scene, three men hold up a Union Forever item, which is surrounded by flowers and vegetables. One man is holding a small sickle. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: For Union (Offsite-box 7, Item 14)
    Two hands shaking. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: [Cannon firing at house] (Offsite-box 7, Item 64)
    Union cannon with Seward, Lincoln, Scott & Cameron on it firing at a house with 'Disunion' on it, with Jeff Davis over the door. Boards with a variety of names on them are flying into the air. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: The Union is as Good as Wheat. (Offsite-box 7, Item 39)
    Simple rendering of a stalk of wheat. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Clear the Track - Union For Ever (Offsite-box 7, Item 30)
    A train with human arms and an American flag running down the Secessionists that look like demons and other unpleasant creatures. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Peace Maker of '76 and '61. (Offsite-box 7, Item 62)
    Image of a cannon. Beige envelope with blue ink. Image on top left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Union (Offsite-box 7, Item 70)
    Shamrock with the words 'North', 'South' and 'Border States' on each of its three petals. Cream envelope with green ink. Image on left side.
  - Miscellaneous Union: Our "Commissioner" to the Confederate States. (Offsite-box 7, Item 68)
    Image of a cannon. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Ross, John, publisher
  - Portraits--A to B: Parson Brownlow. (Offsite-box 5, Item 31)
    Portrait of Parson Brownlow in front of the American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: James Buchanan. Judas. James Buchanan. Judas. (Offsite-box 5, Item 35)
    Portrait of James Buchanan labeled "Judas." White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Jno. Bell (Offsite-box 5, Item 17)
    Portrait of John Bell with "traitor" stamped across his forehead. Yellow envelope with black and red ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Col. E. D. Baker, Killed at the battle of Ball's Bluff, Virginia, October 21st, 1861. (Offsite-box 5, Item 11)
    Liberty weeps, draping her arm and an American flag over a portrait of E. D. Baker. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Col. Birney's Twenty-Third Regiment P.V. (Offsite-box 5, Item 23)
    Portrait of D. B. Birney. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Col. Robert Anderson (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Col. Robert Anderson and a fort with a flag that says Sumter. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: John Brown. (Offsite-box 5, Item 30)
    Portrait of John Brown. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Scott & Anderson (Offsite-box 5, Item 10)
    Portraits of Winfield Scott and Robert Anderson inset over the American flag. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Stimson & Co., copyright holder
  - Portraits--A to B: Lieut. Frank Brownell (Offsite-box 5, Item 33)
    Portrait of Frank Brownell. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--A to B: J. C. Breckinridge (Offsite-box 5, Item 29)
    Portrait of J. C. Breckinridge with "traitor" stamped vertically across him. White envelope with black and red ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: The Bragg fruit of Palmetto Tree-son (Offsite-box 5, Item 27)
    Braxton Bragg hanging from a palm tree. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--A to B: Col. Birney, Col. Baxter, Col. Gosline (Offsite-box 5, Item 22)
    Portraits of D. B. Birney, Baxter, and Gosline. White envelope with black ink. Image across top.
  - Portraits--A to B: Burnside (Offsite-box 5, Item 37)
    Portrait of Ambrose Burnside. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--A to B: [N. P. Banks] (Offsite-box 5, Item 13)
    Portrait of Nathaniel Prentiss Banks. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on top-left. Embossed decoration on seal.
    Creator: Union Stationary Depot
  - Portraits--Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant de: Why Johnny, what have you been doing? (Offsite-box 5, Item 10)
    Woman approaching two boys, one of whom is badly beaten-up. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant de: G. T. Beauregard and his shadow. (Offsite-box 5, Item 11)
    G. T. Beauregard, holding his sword and wearing a pirate's hat, casts a shadow that looks like a monkey. Cream envelope with gray ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant de: Boar-egard Throwing up intrenchments. (Offsite-box 5, Item 9)
    A wild boar vomiting. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant de: G. T. Blow-regard (Offsite-box 5, Item 12)
    An animal/devil in uniform, blowing a bugle with a Confederate flag attached. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Portraits--Butler, Benjamin Franklin: One of the F. F. V.'s after his contraband. (Offsite-box 5, Item 3)
    African-American boy clings to the leg of General Butler. Butler extends his sword to fend-off slave owner with whip and dog. Beige envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Redenburgh, William
  - Portraits--Butler, Benjamin Franklin: Gen. Butler (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Benjamin Butler surrounded by American flags, eagle, weapons, musical instruments. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--C to D: Cain of Baltimore (Offsite-box 5, Item 2)
    "Cain" standing in foreground of battlefield attracting the smoke of secession, as Union smoke goes into the air.
    Creator: Gibson & Co.
  - Portraits--C to D: Sons of Erin! (Offsite-box 5, Item 4)
    Portrait of Michael Corcoran. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--C to D: Col. Du Pont (Offsite-box 5, Item 6)
    Portrait of Samuel Francis Du Pont. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--C to D: (Offsite-box 5, Item 3)
    Portrait of Henry Clay. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--C to D: Captain Dupont. (Offsite-box 5, Item 7)
    Portrait of Samuel Francis Du Pont. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--C to D: General Dix (Offsite-box 5, Item 5)